Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太は➡
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
数々の困難を
なんとかくぐり抜け➡
Having overcome multiple obstacles, he's a step closer to a lunar mission.
月ミッションへの新たな一歩を
踏み出そうとしている＞
＜一方 日本人初の
ひびと
ﾑｰﾝｳｫｰｶｰとなった日々人は➡
Meanwhile, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker, but he has an accident and nearly dies.
月面で事故に遭い
死の瀬戸際まで追い詰められる｡➡
きかん
地球に帰還したものの
事故の影響は➡
After returning to Earth, he discovers the accident has left him traumatized.
心の奥深くに刻み込まれていた＞
As things stand, since he cannot participate in EVA, he's barred from lunar missions.
＜このままでは船外活動ができず
月ミッションには加われない＞
＜日々人は この事実を
兄･六太にも伏せたまま➡
Hibito keeps this information a secret from his
brother, as he heads to chilly Russia to recover.
かつての自分を取り戻すべく
極寒の地 ロシアへと向かった＞
なんば
＜宇宙飛行士の娘は➡
The astronaut's daughter glided through the air.
フワフワと宙を舞った＞
＜月の重力に調子こいて
何度も飛び跳ねた➡
Kind of like what I was doing back on the moon.
あの時の俺みたいに＞
And then, she began to spin.
＜気がつけば
彼女は回り続けていた＞
＜あまりにも軽やかで
無重量空間にでもいるような＞
Her movements were so light,
she seemed to be dancing in zero gravity.
《全然違うな…
ビデオの中のオリガと》
This Olga is completely different than the one in the videos...
Behind the scenes, Olga kept working hard.
《オリガは｢見えないふんばり｣を
続けてきたんだな》
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
#78 Out of Time
Great job!
(客)おつかれさま～！
(客)おつかれさまでした！
Bravo!
ポリーナ よかったわよ！
That was wonderful, Paulina!
(ﾎﾟﾘｰﾅ)うまく踊れた！
I didn't screw up...
(ﾉﾝﾅ)ママー！パパー！
Mama! Papa!
(ｴﾐｰﾘｱ)よかったわよ オリガ｡
That was brilliant, Olga.
(オリガ)ヒビチョフ…｡
Hibichov...
You were watching my performance?
(ｵﾘｶﾞ)見てたの？ヒビチョフも!?
そうよ｡
That's right.
たいしたもんだよ オリガ｡
びっくりした｡
That was impressive, Olga...
What a pleasant surprise.
You should have told me you were coming.
来るなら来るって
言っといてよね｡
Darn it... I'm wearing a kid's shirt today!
《しまった！今日のシャツ
ちょっとガキっぽい！》
それじゃあ 俺はこれで｡
Well, I need to get going.
あっ どこ行くの？ヒビチョフ！
Where are you going, Hibichov?
ちょっとね
寄り道して帰るんだよ｡
Nowhere important...
I just have a stop to make before I go home.
I'm coming with you.
(オリガ)私も行く｡
Huh?
Come and try some!
(売り子)いらっしゃ～い
いらっしゃ～い｡
(オリガ)｢イエーイ｣って
言わないね｡いつ言うの？
You still haven't said, "Yay."
When will you?
(ｵﾘｶﾞ)アニメのヒビットなんて
しょっちゅう言ってるよ｡➡
The cartoon Hibbit says it all the time.
逃げる時でも言ってるのに｡
He even says it when he's running away.
なんだよ 詳しいな｡
見てないんじゃなかったの？
Oh, you sound like an expert...
I thought you didn't watch the show.
見てないよ あんなガキのアニメ｡
見てないけど噂で知ってる｡
I don't watch that kiddie junk.
I don't watch it, but I've heard about it.
Here you are.
(ｳｪｲﾄﾚｽ)お待たせしました｡➡
大人の苦味
ﾌﾞﾗｯｸｺｰﾋｰでございます｡
Two adult coffees served black.
(ｵﾘｶﾞ)ねえ ロシアには
ずっといるの？
So, do you plan to stay in Russia?
No, at some point, I'll have to go back to Houston.
いや いつかは
ヒューストンに帰るよ｡
(ｵﾘｶﾞ)それって いつ？
When would that be?
わかんない｡
(ｵﾘｶﾞ)なにそれ 変なの｡
Don't know.
Why not? You're so weird.
You see, I'm suffering from a small disorder.
実は俺 ちょっとした
神経症があってね｡
そいつを治しに ここに来た｡
I came here to cure myself.
ふ～ん…｡苦っ！
Bitter.
でも ちょっとしたものなら
すぐ治って元気になるよね｡
But if it's a small disorder, you should be cured in no time.
Yeah, you're right.
ああ そうだな｡ハハ…｡
うわぁ…｡
言っとくけど私
買ってなんて頼んでないからね｡
Just so we're clear, I didn't ask you to buy me these.
でも ありがとう これ｡
But thanks!
These boots are crazy!
バヤイよ このブーツ！
欲しかったやつよ！
I really wanted them.
アハハハ！ウフフフ！
《こうなるとやっぱり
１５才って感じだな》
In some ways, she still acts like a girl of fifteen.
あれ…青空が出てるよ｡
Huh?
The sky's clearing up...
(ｵﾘｶﾞ)そりゃあ出るでしょ｡
What's so strange about that?
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)悪いがヒビチョフ➡
Sorry, Hibichov.
ボリューム
｢オリガの成長記録Ｖｏｌ.２｣は
見せることができん｡
I can't let you see Volume 2 of Olga's childhood.
なんでよ｡
Why not?
すげ～気になるよ｡
あの１０才のオリガが➡
You got me really curious...
How did Olga at ten become the Olga I saw on stage?
どうやってあそこまで
成長したのか｡
だろう？
気持ちはわかるが…｡
That's it.
I understand how you feel.
But Olga learned I showed you Volume 1 without permission...
ワン
実は Ｖｏｌ.１を 黙ってお前に
見せたことがオリガにバレてな…｡
超怒られた｡
She went ballistic...
What?
《無断で見せたのかよ》
He didn't ask her first?
ところで ヒビチョフ
こいつを かけろ｡
So, Hibichov, can you put these on?
は？なにこれ？
What are these?
まあ 気にせずかけるんだ｡
Just put them on.
What's this about?
なんなんだよ？
This way.
こっちだ｡
どこ行くの？
Where are we going?
よし ここでいいだろう｡
ＯＫだ ヒビチョフ｡
Okay, that's far enough.
Good job, Hibichov!
ワン
おめでとう レベル１ 合格だ｡
Congratulations, you've passed Level 1.
(飛行士)おめでとう｡
(研究員)レベル１ 合格と｡
Congratulations...
Level 1, cleared.
Wh-What? Wh-What?
な 何？何？
見ろ！
Look.
This is the distance you couldn't walk in a pressure suit.
よあつ
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)お前が与圧服を着て
歩けなかった距離だ｡
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)それを今 お前は難なく
歩いてきた｡➡
But just now, you had no trouble with that distance.
レベル１！
Level 1!
｢グラサンならば歩ける｣という
ことがわかった｡
We've learned that you can walk that far while wearing sunglasses.
そりゃあ歩けるよ｡
当たり前じゃん｡
I would hope so...
That's as easy as it gets.
Hold on.
おっと 忘れたかヒビチョフ
今のお前には➡
Have you forgotten?
At the moment,
｢与圧服を着て歩く｣という
ごく当たり前のことが➡
you can't perform the easy task of walking around in a pressure suit.
できないんだぞ｡
グラサンだって➡
Until we tried it, we weren't sure you could walk around in sunglasses.
やってみなければ
わからんところだ｡
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)こっちに来て これを見ろ
ヒビチョフ｡
Come look at this.
Isn't it exciting?
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)どうだ 楽しそうだろう？➡
We have everything, from stuff that has nothing to do with space,
全く宇宙と関係ない物から
レプリカの宇宙服まである｡➡
to fake spacesuits.
The crew helped assemble this collection for you.
お前のために
みんなが集めてくれたんだ｡➡
バカげてると思うか？
茶番だと？➡
Does it seem stupid to you?
A waste of time?
だが これをやるのが
今のお前の現実だ｡
But it's the reality you face now
受け入れろ｡
Man up.
大事なのは｢できる｣という
経験を得ること｡
The experience is what matters.
レベル２は これだ｡
Here's Level 2...
シルクハットと鼻メガネ｡
A top hat and Groucho glasses.
This time, you'll also cover your nose and head, so there's no telling what could happen.
今度は鼻と頭も覆われるから
どうなるかわからんぞ｡
You seem to be enjoying this.
なんか…ちょっと楽しんでない？
ああ 楽しみながら
克服しようではないか｡
Yeah!
Let's have some fun while we help you get over this.
パニック障害など｡ハハハ…！
よ～し｡
Okay...
やってやる｡
I'm in.
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)鼻メガネの紳士
ヒビチョフがレベル２｡➡
Level 2: Marx Brother Hibichov.
余裕のクリアだった！➡
Piece of cake.
スリー
レベル３のダイバーヒビチョフ➡
Level 3: Diver Hibichov.
フォー
レベル４の銀行強盗ヒビチョフ｡➡
Level 4: Bank Robber Hibichov.
ファイブ
さらには レベル５ アメフト
ヒビチョフも 問題なく合格｡
And Level 5: NFL Hibichov.
They've all been cleared.
あしたからも様々な
ヒビチョフの旅は続くだろう｡
Tomorrow, we'll continue Hibichov's journey to become Cosmonaut Hibichov.
そして目指すべき コスモノート
ヒビチョフにいたるまで➡
Until then, we'll drink every night.
共に 酒を交わし続けよう｡
カンパーイ！
Cheers!
(一同)カンパーイ！
Say, did you come to Russia to dress up in costumes?
ねえ ヒビチョフはコスプレして
遊んでるの？ロシアに来て｡
まあ そう思われても
仕方ねぇよな 不本意ながら｡
Well, unfortunately, I can see why you might ask that...
Honestly, I was pretty worried about Level 5.
正直 レベル５のアメフトの時は
ヒヤヒヤしたぞ｡➡
お前が発作を起こしたのは➡
Since you started showing panic after putting on the pressure suit helmet.
与圧服のヘルメットを
かぶってからだったからな｡
アメフトのヘルメットを
クリアできたんだ｡
You were able to walk around in a football helmet.
これは大きな進歩だぞ
ヒビチョフ！
That's a big step forward, Hibichov!
まだまだ やれたよ きょう｡
テン
レベル１０ぐらいまで｡
I could have kept going today...
All the way to Level 10.
できたところで 気持ちよく
終われたならいいんじゃない？
It's best to end on a positive note.
その通り！
Exactly!
Experiencing success is important.
大事なのは
｢できる｣という経験を得ること｡
Now, drink up, Hibichov...
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)さあ飲め ヒビチョフ！
あしたは 剣道ヒビチョフから
始めるぞ｡ハハハハ！
Tomorrow, we'll start with Kendo Hibichov.
見送りなんて
いいっつってんのに｡
You don't need to walk me home...
It doesn't make sense for a kid to walk a thirty-year-old man home.
変だよ 三十男が
子どもに送ってもらうなんて｡
Don't worry about it!
気にしない 気にしない｡
ついてきたいだけだから｡
I just felt like tagging along.
And don't call me a kid.
そして 私を子ども扱いしないで｡
ねえ 次の土曜日にさ
またデートしようよ｡
Hey, next Saturday, let's go on another date.
Huh? Another date...
えっ またって…｡
That counted as a date?
《おとといのあれは
デートだったのか…》
ウラジオストックで遊んで
夜景見て帰んの｡ねっ！
We can visit Vladivostok and take in the night view before heading home.
Okay?
ヒビチョフに買ってもらった
あのクツを そん時におろすんだ｡
I'll wear the boots you bought for me.
Interesting.
なるほど｡でもな～
１５の女の子とデートってのは➡
Still, I'm not crazy about going on a date with a fifteen-year-old.
ちょっと…年の差も倍ちがうよ｡
I'm twice your age.
Well, you're twice my age now.
まあ 今は倍ちがうけどさ➡
ヒビチョフが３５になったら
私はハタチでしょ｡
But when you're thirty-five, I'll be twenty.
もう倍じゃないよ｡➡
You won't be twice my age anymore.
で ヒビチョフが４５の時は
私は３０でしょ｡➡
And when you're forty-five, I'll be thirty.
When you're fifty-five, I'll be forty.
５５の時は４０でしょ｡
When you're sixty-five, I'll be fifty.
６５の時は 私は５０になってて➡
そうなったら
もうあんま変わんないよね｡
At that point, there's hardly any difference.
まあ…そうかも｡
Well... I guess you could put it like that.
あ～あ もう着いちゃったよ｡
ガガーリン像｡
We're already at the Gagarin statue.
じゃあ きょうはここで｡
ありがとう オリガ｡おやすみ｡
Then, I guess that's it.
Thanks, Olga.
Good night.
土曜日 約束ね！
わかったよ｡
You promise to take me out on Saturday?
Okay.
あ そういえばヒビチョフ｡
Oh, Hibichov...
あれ いつ言うの？そろそろ？
When will you say it?
Soon?
Yay!
イエーイ！
バイバーイ！
イエーイ！イエーイ!!アハハ！
Bye-bye!
Yay! Yay!
さて あしたは剣道か｡
Well, it sounds like I have some kendo tomorrow.
ふざけたやり方だけど➡
This approach is silly.
I don't see how I could possibly have an attack in these outfits.
あんな格好で
発作が起こる気がしない｡
From that perspective, I have to say
そう考えたら 与圧服だって…｡
that I think I could handle a pressure suit.
《なんか ちょっと
いけそうな気がしてきたな》
いつまでも
ごまかせると思ってたのか？➡
How long did you expect to fool the rest of us?
時間切れだよ バトラー室長｡
You're out of time, Chief Butler.
私だって調べれば何でもわかる｡➡
I have access to any information I require.
Hibito is not training in the Soyuz in Russia...
今 ヒビトはロシアで ソユーズの
訓練など受けていない｡➡
わずら
精神障害を患って
その治療を内密に済ませるため➡
You sent him away from Houston to secretly undergo rehab for a mental disorder.
ヒューストンから遠ざけた｡
違うか？
Moonbase Program Manager Walter Gates
Am I wrong?
(バトラー)相変わらず 言い方に
トゲがあるな ゲイツ｡
You always sound so accusative, Gates.
兄のムッタや
セス
ＣＥＳ-５１クルーのメンバーに➡
Hibito didn't want to burden his brother, Mutta, and the CES-51 crew with this information.
余計な心配をさせたくないという
そち
ヒビトの願いを尊重しての措置だ｡
Though it is taking longer than expected for him to recover...
思った以上に回復に
時間をとってしまっているが｡
That's why I said that you're out of time.
だから言ってるだろう｡
時間切れなんだよ｡
ヒビトの状態を
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡにも報告した｡
We've reported Hibito's condition to JAXA.
We provided our opinion, and are waiting for a decision to be reached.
こちらの意見も伝え 今は
適正な決断を待っているところだ｡
｢こちらの意見｣とは何だ？
What opinion did we provide?
(役員)え～ みなさん
聞いていると思いますが➡
Well, as I'm sure you've all heard,
南波日々人飛行士について➡
NASA's Moonbase Program Manager
has sent us a communication about astronaut Nanba Hibito.
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡの月面基地プログラム
マネｰジャｰから連絡がありました｡
え～ 彼の話によると➡
The statement says that NASA psychiatrists examined Hibito,
ＮＡＳＡの精神心理担当医が
日々人君を診た結果➡
and that his panic disorder is severe.
日々人君のパニック障害は
重度であり➡
今の状態では かなりの確率で➡
At the moment, their prognosis is that he will never return to space.
宇宙へ飛ぶことは不可能だろう
という診断がなされました｡
しょぐう
そこで 日々人君の処遇を
どうするか決めなければならない｡
So we must decide what to do about Hibito.
(田沼)前線から退いてもらうしか
ないでしょう｡
We'll have to pull him off active duty.
We can't send astronauts who pose a risk.
リスクのある飛行士は使えない｡
国際的な信用問題に関わります｡
Our nation's reliability could come into question.
But Hibito has become a national hero...
だが日々人君は 日本のヒーローに
なってしまってるわけで｡➡
れいぐう
そんな彼が冷遇されてるように➡
We wouldn't want the world to think we're treating him poorly.
世間の目に映ってしまっては
まずいですよ｡
我々の評判が
落ちる結果になりますよ｡
Our reputation will suffer...
(役員)それは同感だ｡
I concur.
もう少し様子を見れませんか｡
Can we wait and see for a bit longer?
ＪＡＸＡの医師が
ＮＡＳＡの医師と協調しながら➡
We should have JAXA doctors assisting NASA's doctors to help him recover.
回復に努めるというのが
本来の筋でしょう｡
ゆうよ
星加君もうその猶予はないんだよ｡
Hoshika, it's too late for that.
田沼…｡
Tanuma...
じゃあ こうしましょう｡
Then, how does this sound?
(原田)それで 日々人さんは
どうなるんですか？
So what will happen to Hibito?
正直 いい結果とは言えんな｡➡
To be frank, it's not good.
田沼の出した｢ｾｰﾌﾃｨｰｽｰﾊﾟｰﾊﾞｲｻﾞｰ｣の
案が通ってしまった｡➡
Tanuma's "Safety Supervisor" proposal was accepted.
もうＮＡＳＡにも
連絡がいってるだろう｡
They're probably already reaching out to NASA.
何すか それ？
What do you mean?
I'd guess this is what NASA will tell Hibito...
おそらくＮＡＳＡからは
日々人君に こう伝えられる｡
せいかん
(星加)｢無事生還した君の月面での
非常時対応は➡
"We'd like to incorporate your emergency response actions into future missions.
将来のミッションに
活かすことができる｡➡
だから 安全担当部門で
セｰフティｰスｰパｰバイザｰとして➡
So would you consider becoming a Safety Supervisor?"
活躍してくれないか｣とか何とか｡
Something along those lines.
あたかも 日々人君の
こうせき
功績に見合った➡
They'll make it sound like an important position, suited to an astronaut of his achievements.
立派なポジションに
ばってき
抜擢するかのような言い方でな｡
ＮＡＳＡから…｡はい｡
It's from NASA...
Yes?
だが その任務に就いたところで➡
But once he's in that position,
基本的に不具合が発生しない限り
目立った仕事はない｡➡
he won't have any important work to do unless something goes terribly wrong.
しかも ほとんどの不具合は
技術的な話だ｡➡
And most issues that arise are technical.
The experts will handle those.
技術屋が問題を解決しておわる｡➡
事情を知らぬ者には 日々人君が
昇格したように見えるだろう｡
People who don't understand the system will see it as a promotion for him.
だが実際 彼は
そのポジションを得て➡
But in reality, this position will rob him of any chance to advance.
活躍の場を失うことになる｡
言いたくはないが
ほとんど飼い殺し状態だ｡
I hate to say it, but his talents will go to waste.
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#79 Olga, Hibito, and Gagarin
Why does Hibichov need to return?!
(ｲｳﾞｧﾝ)＜なぜヒビチョフが
帰らなきゃならんのだ＞
So, are you coming back?
(オリガ)＜ねえ 戻ってくる？＞
＜わかんないんだ どうなるか＞
I don't know what's going to happen.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Olga, Hibito, and Gagarin"
＜ごめんな オリガ＞
I'm sorry, Olga.
Mr. Hibbit!
(ゾウ)出てきたゾウ～！
There they are.
Yay!
(ﾋﾋﾞｯﾄ)イエーイ！
行ってきま～す！
Off we go...
Up.
はい！はい！はい！
こんなところで
ハタあげ訓練の成果が…｡
I see he trained hard with those flags.
心の準備はいいか みんな？
Is everyone prepared?
My nose tells me that launch is imminent.
いよいよ 打ち上げの時だと
私のハナが告げている｡
(ｶﾚﾝｷｬｯﾄ)みんニャ知ってるわよ｡
We already knew that.
There it is...
見えてきたよ！
イエーイ！イエーイ!!
Yay! Yay!
うほ～！カッチョイイぜ～｡
These are so cool!
ハイ どうぞ！
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨｺﾞﾘﾗ)うほう！➡
Here you go.
なんだこのヘルメット!?
きつくて入らないぞ！➡
What's wrong with this helmet?
It's too small for my head.
But I can overcome that with my power!
だが これぐらい
俺さまのパワーで！うほぉ～!!
適当にかぶるんじゃない
バディゴリラ｡
Don't pick a random helmet, Buddy Gorilla!
ヘルメットは みんなの頭の形に
合わせていて それぞれ違うんだ！
Each helmet was designed to fit one astronaut's head.
く く 苦しい…うほ…｡
I-It hurts...
Hey, that's mine.
あ それボクのだね！
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨﾄﾞｯｸﾞ)仕方ない ひっぱるぞ！
Very well, let's pull him out.
He's such a troublemaker...
(ｶﾚﾝｷｬｯﾄ)世話がやけるニャー｡
(一同)せ～の！
Ready, set...
ハ～～ 助かったぜ みんな｡ん？
You saved me, guys!
Wh-What's wrong, guys?
ど どうしたんだ みんな？
さあ いよいよ打ち上げだ！
Okay, it's time for the launch!
イエーイ！
Yay!
イエーイ！待っててよ！
月ウサギ!!あ～｡
Wait for me, space rabbits!
ヘルメット脱いでもいい？
(一同)ダメ!!
Can I remove my helmet?
No!